Guide to the Ella Barksdale Brown Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ella Barksdale Brown Papers
1885-1952
1906-1926
JWJ MSS 41
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.98
(9 boxes)
The Ella Barksdale Brown Papers consist of correspondence, writings, financial papers, newspapers and other materials that document her work as an educator, anti-lynching activist, suffragist, and journalist. The bulk of the papers provide evidence of Brown's activism and involvement with numerous schools, youth groups, war relief, civil rights and community organizations.
Brown, Ella Barksdale, 1871-1966
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Company on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Ella Barksdale Brown (1871-1966)
Ella Barksdale Brown, educator, anti-lynching activist, suffragist, and journalist, was born in Milledgeville, Georgia, and was a member of the first graduating class of Spelman Seminary (later Spelman College) in 1887. According to her obituary, she was born to former slaves, Jefferson Barksdale and Julia Lamar Barksdale on June 22, 1871. Ella Barksdale married John M. Brown in Georgia in 1898, and they moved to Jersey City, New Jersey in 1901 where John worked for the Pullman Company. The couple had four children: Marcia, Jefferson Barksdale, Mildred, and Miriam. Among Brown's accomplishments as an educator and activist, she is credited with introducing the study of African American history to Jersey City public schools. She is also credited with persuading the New Jersey Federation, in 1949, to designate March fifth as Crispus Attucks Day in New Jersey.
Brown was also a journalist who wrote for well known African American newspapers of the early twentieth century including The Chicago Defender and The New York Amsterdam News. A devoted educator, she was sought after by area Jersey City high schools and community organizations to deliver lectures on African American history. Her community and national activism gained her personal acquaintance with some of the leading civil rights proponents and African American leaders of the early twentieth century including W. E. B. Dubois, Booker T. Washington, Paul Robeson and James Weldon Johnson. Some of the community organizations she was most involved with were the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, the Circle for Negro War Relief, the New Jersey Civil Rights Bureau and the National Association of Colored Women.
Additional biographical information obtained from Spelman College is filed in Box 1.
Scope and Contents
The Ella Barksdale Brown Papers document her life as an educator, anti-lynching activist, suffragist and journalist, and span the dates 1885 to 1952, although the bulk is from 1906 to 1926. The papers consist of correspondence, printed material and financial papers documenting Brown's involvement with war relief efforts, teaching, women's rights, civil rights and other social issues mostly pertaining to African Americans during the early twentieth century.
The correspondence documents Ella Barksdale Brown's personal and professional relationships including those with figures and organizations prominent in the civil rights movement. The printed materials document her interest in education and particularly her life as an educator. Her personal writings include two speeches/essays entitled "The Negro's Burden" and "The Negro's Contribution" (both undated) plus other short writings that document her work as a civil rights activist, educator and anti-lynching activist. A group of financial papers document Brown's and her family's ownership of property in New Jersey and Georgia.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence. II. Printed Material. III. Personal Papers.
Atlantic monthly; Chicago defender; Crisis; Dispatch; New York age (New York, N.Y.: 1887); New York Amsterdam news; African Americans -- Education; African American newspapers -- History -- 20th Century; African American women journalists; African American women -- Civil rights -- History -- 20th Century; African American women; African Americans -- Civil rights; African Americans; Civil rights -- New Jersey; Civil rights; Lynching; Suffrage; Jersey City (N.J.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th Century; Educators; Journalists; Suffragists; Brown, Ella Barksdale, 1871-1966; Brown, John Marcus, 1872-1952; Butler, H. R.; Cannon, George Epps, 1869-1925; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915; American Bar Association; American Jewish War Relief and Welfare Board; Atlanta University; Circle for Negro War Relief; Fisk University; Lincoln University (Jefferson City, Mo.); National Association for the Advancement of Colored People; National Medical Association (U.S.); Spelman College
- Correspondence, 1885-1952; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Individuals, Organizations and Financial.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains Ella Barksdale Brown's personal and professional correspondence. The bulk of her correspondence is with various youth organizations, schools, and civil rights and war relief organizations such as the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People and the Circle for Negro War Relief. The correspondence also documents Brown's personal acquaintance with several leaders in the Civil Rights Movement. Other personal correspondents include George E. Cannon, prominent African American physician and clergyman, and H. R. Butler, physician and one of the founding members of the National Medical Association.
  Among the correspondence is a typed letter, signed by Booker T. Washington, thanking Brown for making good use of some pictures the Tuskegee Institute sent her; a letter from Sarah L. Hunt describing the funeral of Booker T. Washington; and a hand-written letter, signed by Paul Robeson, apologizing for missing a dinner given by Brown.
  There is also financial correspondence including letters from various mortgage companies and banks. Ella Barksdale Brown and John M. Brown were home owners and the financial correspondence indicates that they may have owned at least two properties in New Jersey. There is also some financial correspondence regarding land and a home mortgage in Georgia, probably belonging to her father.
  Some correspondence is to John M. Brown and to the Browns' children.
  - Individuals
    - Adams, Cora, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Belcher, May, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Berry, J. C., 1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Blackshear, J., 1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bowles, Eva, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Brisbane, A., 1913 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Brown, Carrie, 1920,1922 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Brown, Jefferson Barksdale, 1925,1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Brown, J. T., 1919 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Butler, H. R., 1919 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Byrd, William A., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Cannon, George E., 1916,1918 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Clemmons, S. C., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Collier, N. W., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Daniel, M., 1915 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Dubois, W. E. B., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Fisher, W., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Flint, Rachel, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Freeman, Charles S., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Gibson, Chas, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Green, E. E., 1915 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Gregory, N. B., 1915 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Gunnell, J. C., 1917 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Hamblin, William, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Hartgrove, Robert S., 1919 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Hayes, Elizabeth Hart, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Holland, Edward, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Hooper, Warren G., 1914-1918 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Hunt, Sarah L., 1915 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Hunton, A. W., 1914, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Jones, A. J., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Jones, C. Bion, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Jones, C. M., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Jones, Emma, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Jones, Mrs. John, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Layton, Julia M., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Maddox, Victoria, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Mottley, Fitz W., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Moylan, James J., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Owens, J. H., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Pratt, Clyde A., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Proctor, Henry H., 1917 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Randolph, Florence, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Rice, Melvin A., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Rice, R. Anderson, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Robeson, Paul, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Saunders, Selena, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Schwinn, Mrs. P., 1919 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Sears, Adelaide E., 1919 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Simpson, M., 1903,1908 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Snyder, Henry, 1914,1917 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Spraggins, Traverse A., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Stoney, Rosa, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Tapley, Lucy Hale, 1914,1920 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Walker, C. T., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Washington, Booker T., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Washington, J. M., undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - White, William J., 1914 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Williams, Marcia Brown, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Williams, Thomas H., 1917 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Worthy, Maud, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Unidentified, 1915-1918 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Postcards, 1906-1933 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Organizations
    - 37th Infantry Welfare League, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - American Bar Association, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - American Jewish War Relief and Welfare Board, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Box Office Attractions Company, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Chicago Advertising Agency, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - The Chicago Defender, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Circle for Negro War Relief, 1918-1920 (Box 2, Folder 71-73)
    - Committee of One Hundred of Hudson County, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Federation of Colored Organizations of New Jersey, 1918, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Frederick Douglass Film Company, undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - The Jersey Journal, 1914, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Lincoln Institute (now Lincoln University), 1914 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Manual Training and Industrial School for Youth (Bordentown, N.J.), 1917 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, 1917-1925 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - National Medical Association, 1918,1919 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Negro Welfare League, 1917-1919 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - New Jersey Civil Rights Bureau, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - New International Yearbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - The New York Age, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Southern Sugar Company, undated (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Spelman Seminary (now Spelman College), 1914 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Young Men's Christian Association, 1914-1917 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Envelopes, 1914-1952 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Financial
    - A. T. Holt & Company, 1914-1917 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - C. Howard Slater Real Estate and Insurance, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Commercial Investment Trust Incorporated, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Commonwealth Insurance Company, 1923,1924 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Continental Casualty Company, 1917-1927 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Department of Streets and Public Improvements of Jersey City, 1918-1921 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - E. O. Smith Real Estate and Insurance, 1919-1926 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Faulkner & Cook Real Estate Company, 1921-1926 (Box 2, Folder 97-98)
    - Federal Land and Improvement Company, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Fisk & Fisk, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - J. S. Bartlett and Company, 1921-1923 (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - Lincoln State Bank of Chicago, 1916-1921 (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - National Union Fire Insurance Company, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - Ocean & Bay Realty Corp., 1915 (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - O. L. Schwencke Land and Investment Company, 1921-1922 (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - Phoenix Assurance Company Limited, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 107)
    - Pilgrim Health and Life Insurance Company, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 108)
    - R. M. O'Brien and Company, 1918-1923 (Box 3, Folder 109)
    - Trust Company of New Jersey, 1926,1937 (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - Union Trust and Hudson County National Bank, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - W. A. Barclay Sanitary Plumbing, Steam and Hot Water Heating, 1916-1918 (Box 3, Folder 112)
    - West-Rogers Realty Company, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 113)
    - Winship Insurance Company, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 114)
    - Unidentified, 1892-1926 (Box 3, Folder 115)
- Series II. Printed Material, 1906-1931; 1; (4 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Academic Institutions and Other Printed Material.
  This series consists of university periodicals, brochures and other informational flyers from institutions such as Atlanta University, Fisk University and Lincoln Institute that document Brown's interests as an educator and activist, as well as her children's education. The series also contains copies of literary and news publications including Crisis, Dispatch, and Colored American, and a collection of newspapers and newspaper clippings. The clippings further show her interests and concerns including lynchings, African-American cultural events, World War I, and other stories covering race issues during the early twentieth century.
  - Academic Institutions
    - Atlanta University, 1913-1926 (Box 4, Folder 116-120)
    - Fisk University, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - Lincoln High School (New Jersey), 1916 (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Lincoln Institute (now Lincoln University), 1914 (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Reed Home and Industrial School, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Rice Industrial and Literary Institute, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Spelman Seminary, 1911-1922 (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - Unity School of Christianity, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 127)
  - Other Printed Material
    - The Atlantic Monthly, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - Business Cards, undated (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - The Colored American Magazine, 1906 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - The Crisis, 1915-1931 (Box 5, Folder 131-132)
    - Delta Sigma Theta Bulletin, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 133)
    - The Dispatch, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - Event Flyers, 1909-1920 (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - The Literary Digest, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Pamphlets, 1914-1926 (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Roth Memory Course, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - St. Mark's Messenger, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Town Topics, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Clippings, 1914-1930 (Box 8, Folder 141-146)
    - Newspapers, 1914-1930 (Box 9, Folder 147-160)
- Personal Papers, 1906-1924; Series III; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Writings and Financial Papers.
  This series contains a small number of Ella Barksdale Brown's writings. They include two undated handwritten speeches/essays discussing various issues pertaining to African Americans during the early twentieth century. The series also includes some checks, check receipts, income tax forms and organization payment books.
  - Writings
    - "Jersey City Notes", 1919,1920 (Box 6, Folder 161)
    - "The Negro's Burden", undated (Box 6, Folder 162)
    - "The Negro's Contribution", undated (Box 6, Folder 163)
    - Personal writings and related material, undated,1919 (Box 6, Folder 164-165)
  - Financial Papers
    - Checks, 1921-1924 (Box 6, Folder 166-169)
    - Checks, 1921-1924 (Box 7, Folder 170)
    - Knights of Pythias Financial Book, 1906-1919 (Box 7, Folder 171)
    - The Commonwealth Beneficial Association, 1922-1923 (Box 7, Folder 172)
    - Receipts, 1914-1929 (Box 7, Folder 173)
    - Taxes, 1921-1926 (Box 7, Folder 174)